Finding Aid for the Yvar Mikhashoff Collection of Tangos, 1983-1991
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Yvar Mikhashoff Collection of Tangos, 1983-1991
Mus. Arc. 1.10
Mikhashoff, Yvar
5 boxes (250 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains photocopies of musical scores for 127 tangos for solo piano from 127 composers. The collection also documents the process by which Mikhashoff commissioned and performed the tangos. It includes correspondence, Mikhashoff's research into the history of the tango, and performance materials (i.e. programs and reviews). Composers commissioned for this project include Milton Babbitt, Lukas Foss, Otto Luening, Conlon Nancarrow, Luis de Pablo,and Nils Vigeland.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the estate of Yvar Mikhashoff, 1994
Accruals and Additions
No further major accruals are expected to this collection. Revisions of the tangos are occassionally received from composers. They are housed with the original score.
Biographical Note
Yvar-Emilian Mikhashoff was born Ronald McKay in Troy, near Albany, New York in 1941. He began piano studies with Betty Weir and Stanley Hummel in Albany. Mikhashoff studied at the Eastman School of Music in 1959 and in the 1961 academic year, he studied piano at the Juilliard School in New York City. He also had a career as a ballroom dancer from 1962-1965. In 1964 Mikhashoff entered the University of Houston, where he earned a B.M. in 1967 and a M.M in composition in 1968.
Receiving a Fulbright scholarship, he studied the music of the French Impressionists with Nadia Boulanger. After his return to the United States, Mikhashoff earned a Doctor of Musical Arts from the University of Texas at Austin in August 1973. In the Fall of 1973 Mikhashoff was appointed Assistant Professor at the State University of New York at Buffalo. Based in Buffalo until his death in 1993, Mikhashoff had an international performing career which led him to promote new music and American music around the world.
In 1982 Mikhashoff had finished a project of commissioned piano pieces, The Buffalo Piano Collection, and was inspired to create a new project. Mikhashoff collaborated with the publishing firm Quadrivium Press, whose contact was Ed Snider, to commission composers from all over the world to write piano pieces based on a dance form, the tango. Mikhashoff's brief but rewarding career as a ballroom dancer was the impetus for centering the project on the tango and composers were enthusiastic to contribute to this collection. Eighty-eight tangos by composers from 30 countries were officially premiered on April 14, 1985 at the North American New Music Festival. Mikhashoff toured internationally performing the tangos and to this date the collection totals 127 tangos for solo piano. It was intended that the tangos be published in a multi-volume set by Quadrivium Press. However, the publication was never issued.
Scope and Content Note
The core of this collection contains photocopies of musical scores for 127 tangos for solo piano submitted to Yvar Mikhashoff between the years 1984-1991. Starting in 1983, Mikhashoff commissioned tangos from composers such as Robert Ashley, Milton Babbitt, Lukas Foss, Otto Luening, Luis de Pablo, and Nils Vigeland. The majority of the original manuscripts are held by Anthony de Mare, pianist, pupil and friend of Mikhashoff; however, this collection does contain manuscripts worthy of mention: The Three Fathers by Gilberto Mendes, Del Tingo al Tango by William Ortiz, Red-sweet Tango by Jorges Peixinho, Tangonetta by Poul Ruders, and Collage-tango by Tadeusz Wielecki. Other unique items in this collection include the sketches of Tiefertango by Oliver Knussen and autographed photocopies of tangos by Mikael Edlund, Tom Johnson, Betsy Jolas, John Myhill, Luis De Pablo, and Marcello Panni.
The collection also contains nine tangos arranged for a chamber ensemble and three tangos for voice and piano. Mikhashoff performed these works on April 15, 1987 with members of the Houston Symphony Orchestra in Houston, Texas. These arrangements have been collated to create another series within this collection.
Correspondence in the collection includes letters from composers, signed agreements for the commission, and/or biographical information about the composers sent to Mikhashoff and/or Ed Snider dated 1983-1989. Not all composers represented in this collection of tangos are included in the correspondence and not all composers with a correspondence folder submitted a tango. After the collection was donated to the Music Library, attempts to contact composers have resulted in updated information for the composer and revised versions of a few tangos previously submitted to the collection. These include Tango para Ivar by Orlando Jacinto Garcia, Moon-Dark Tango by Anthony Genge, Tin-pan Tango by Adrian Jack, and Tango Blue by Charles Sepos.
Mikhashoff's research into the history of the tango included journal articles, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, and a playbill and ticket stub for the Broadway show Tango Argentino. In addition, Mikhashoff collected images of couples dancing the tango and images of works of art that were inspired by or depicted the tango. Mikhashoff incorporated much of this information into his performances of the tango collection, including a lecture on the history of the tango and a slide show.
The performances were always evolving as more tangos were submitted to the collection. As a result, Mikhashoff created many lists of tangos received from 1984 to 1987. He saved programs and reviews of his performances, wrote a preface to the collection and had covers and postcards designed by Bud Jacobs, intended to be used for publishing.
Arrangement
Arranged into six series:
I. Musical scores of tangos
II. Arrangements of tangos
III. Correspondence
IV. Research materials
V. Study scores
VI. Performance materials
Container List
- Musical scores of the tangos, 1984-1991, I.; Box 1-3, Folder 1-143
  Musical scores of tangos submitted to Yvar Mikhashoff for his International Tango Project.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by composer name.
  - Aharonián, Coriún, 1940- Y ahora? (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Beth, 1950- Belgian tango (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ashley, Robert, 1930- Improvement (Don leaves Linda). Act II. Scene 20: North Berlin/A Tango, Text only (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Attinello, Paul Tango: A slow hot wind (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Austin, Larry Tango violento (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Babbitt, Milton, 1916- It takes twelve to tango (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barce, Ramón Tango para Yvar (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bell, Larry, 1952- First tango in London (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bennett, Richard Rodney Tango after Syrinx (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Berkman, Robert Thorn-torn lips (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Biscardi, Chester Incitation to desire (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bley, Carla Reactionary tango (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boehmer, Konrad, 1941- Tango deslavado y moroso (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bolcom, William The dead moth tango (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bredemeyer, Reiner, 1929- Thango tangente (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bright, Colin Tango-dreaming (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bruce, Neely Tango variation (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Burgess, Anthony, 1917- Tango for pianoforte (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Busby, Gerald Cometango (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cabuche, Mario Tango '85 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cage, John Perpetual tango, Based on no. 16 of Erik Satie's Sports et Divertissements (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Cage, John Perpetual tango, Manuscript and copies of arrangement realized for grand staff (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chadabe, Joel The long ago and far away tango (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Christoff, Dimiter, 1933- Tango for you, friends (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Clapperton, James, 1968- ... the gay foppery of summer is flown (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cohen, Douglas, 1959- Tango paseo (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Copland, Aaron, 1900- Hear ye, hear ye! (Ballet). Scene VII. Tango, Manuscript of arrangement for solo piano by Yvar Mikhashoff (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Copland, Aaron, 1900- Hear ye, hear ye! (Ballet). Scene VII. Tango, Photocopy of arrangement by Yvar Mikhashoff (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Copland, Aaron, 1900- Hear ye, hear ye! (Ballet). Scene VII. Tango, Photocopy of manuscript, arranged for 2 pianos by composer (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Curran, Alvin S., 1938- Tango no. 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Davies, Hugh, 1943- Master Domenico's humpback (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Duckworth, William Tango voices (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Edlund, Mikael, 1950- Orchids in the embers (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Edlund, Mikael, 1950- Orchids in the embers, Autographed photocopy (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fennelly, Brian Tangoblique (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ferrero, Lorenzo Rock my tango (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Finch, Douglas Tango (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fine, Vivian, 1913- Tango with the frog prince (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Finnissy, Michael Tango (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Foss, Lukas, 1922- Tango from Curriculim Vitae, For accordion, excerpted and arranged by the composer (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Ganz, Isabelle Go away tango (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - García, Orlando Jacinto Tango para Ivar, Includes revision submitted by the composer in 2002 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Genge, Anthony, 1952- Tango, Includes revision titled Moon-dark tango submitted by the composer in 2002 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Gideon, Miriam, 1906- Tango langoroso (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Godøy, Rolf Inge First tango (Silken slippers) (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Goeyvaerts, Karel Aquarius tango (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Goldstein, Malcolm, 1936- Can it be done in public? (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Golub, Peter, 1952- The Barrow Street tango (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Haskins, Robert, 1960- Automatic tango (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Hill, Jackson, 1941- Tango no tango (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Hiller, Lejaren Arthur, 1924- Tango for piano (Staircase tango) (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hodkinson, Sydney Habanera melancolica (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Horwood, Michael S Horizontal tango (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Hunt, Jerry, 1943- Tango (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Jack, Adrian Tin-pan tango, Includes copy submitted a performance copy in 2002 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Jaggard, David Elastic Tango (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Jeney, Zoltán, 1943- Philip Marlowe tracks down Yvar's last tango (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Jenkins, Leroy Tango, rango, bango (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Johnson, Tom, 1939- Tango (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Johnson, Tom, 1939- Tango, Dedicated copy autographed by the composer (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Jolas, Betsy Tango si (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Jolas, Betsy Tango si, Dedicated copy autographed by the composer (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Kasemets, Udo Tangovariables (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Keane, David, 1943- Los rayos de sol (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Kelemen, Milko Tango (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - King, John, 1953 Nov. 28- Tango to Argentina (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Knussen, Oliver Tiefertango (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Knussen, Oliver Tiefertango, Autographed sketches (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Kondo, Jo, 1947- Tango mnemonic (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Kurtz, Eugene, 1923- Etude in tangotime (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Lake, Lawrence, 1943- Tango (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Lee, Noël, 1924- Tango imprint (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Lidov, David, 1941- Tango (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Loudova, Ivana Tango music (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Luening, Otto, 1900- Tango (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - McCandless, Michael, 1957-1993 Tangentangle (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Mellnäs, Arne ... Ingen dans på roser Baile sobre rosas: tango (Not a bed of roses tango) (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Melnyk, Lubomyr Swan dance (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Mencherini, Fernando, 1949- Das zweite Zimmer (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Mendes, Gilberto, 1922- The three fathers (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Mendes, Gilberto, 1922- The three fathers, Original manuscript, unsigned (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Mott, David Tango: under the winter moon (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Mumford, Jeffrey, 1955- Tango variations (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Myhill, John El gran macho (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Myhill, John El gran macho, Autographed copy (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Nancarrow, Conlon, 1912- Tango (?) (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Nancarrow, Conlon, 1912- Tango?, Manuscript rewritten by Yvar Mikhashoff (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Nash, Peter Paul, 1950- Icebreak tango (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Newlin, Dika, 1923- Tango for Johannes (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Nichifor, Serbin Tango for Yvar (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Nobre, Marlos, 1939- Tango para piano, op. 61 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Noon, David, 1946- Machine-tango (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Nørgård, Per, 1932- Without jealousy (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Nyman, Michael A neat slice of tango (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Orbán, György Suite for piano (1985): Nr. 2 - Kriminältango (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Ortiz, William Del tingo al tango (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Ortiz, William Del tingo al tango, Autographed manuscript (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Pablo, Luis de Tango (de J.H.) (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Pablo, Luis de Tango (de J.H.), Autographed photocopy (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Palmer, Robert, 1915- Interrupted tango (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Panni, Marcello Tangomix (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Panni, Marcello Tangomix, Dedicated copy (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Paquette, Wayne Movie tango (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Peixinho, Jorge Rosado M., 1940- Red-sweet tango (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Peixinho, Jorge Rosado M., 1940- Red-sweet tango, Original manuscript (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Pender, Scott Tango: Ms. Jackson dances for the people (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Pousseur, Henri Tango de Jeanne-La-Sybille (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Raschke, Frank Tango auf drei Beinem (Three-legged tango) (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Rasmussen, Karl Aage Triple tango (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Rosenhaus, Steven The kiss (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Ross, Valerie A tangorine for Yvar (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Ruders, Poul, 1949- Tangonetta (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Ruders, Poul, 1949- Tangonetta, Unsigned manuscript (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Rudhyar, Dane, 1895- Tango d'Antan (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Rugeles, Alfredo Tanguitis (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Rzewski, Frederic Steptangle (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Exiles cafe tango (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Sáry, László Tango (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Savaskan, Sinan The square root impressions with tears (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Schimmel, William Fromage dangereux (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Schwartz, Elliott, 1936- Tango with interruptions (or Interrupted tango) (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Sellars, James, 1943- Tango (in memoriam Schoenberg?) (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Sepos, Charles, 1950- Blue tempation tango, Includes revision titled Tango Blue, submitted by composer in 1991 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Shapey, Ralph, 1921- Tango variations on a cantus (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Singer, Malcolm It takes two to (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - Smith, Dave, 1949- Tango (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Speach, Bernadette, 1948- To tango or not ... (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Stockhausen, Karlheinz, 1928- Tierkreis. Nr. 5: Zwillinge-Gemin; Nr. 7: Löwe-Leo, Includes a version for single staff and a version realized for grand staff (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Sullivan, Ken Maracaibo (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - Thomson, Virgil, 1896- Two sentimental tangos (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - Thorne, Francis Meditation-tango (Box 3, Folder 131)
  - Tiensuu, Jukka Fantango (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Tisné, Antoine Sarcastic tango (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Tragtenberg, Livio, 1961- Ornytango (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Tyranny, Blue Gene, 1945- The more he sings, the more he cries, the better he feels tango (Box 3, Folder 135)
  - Vigeland, Nils Tango a' deux (Box 3, Folder 136)
  - Weinzweig, John, 1913- Tango for two (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - White, John, 1936- Piano sonata no. 108: Reminiscenza di tempo di tango (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Wielecki, Tadeusz Collage-tango (Box 3, Folder 139)
  - Wielecki, Tadeusz Collage-tango, Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - Wigglesworth, Frank, 1918- Tango triste (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Wolpe, Stefan Tango (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - Zimmermann, Walter, 1949- Puritaner-tango (Box 3, Folder 143)
- Arrangements of tangos, 1983-1991, II.; Box 3, Folder 144-154
  Tangos performed 15 April, 1987, with members of the Houston Symphony Orchestra and other special guests. Includes musical scores and parts for Mikhashoff arrangements of seven tangos for chamber ensemble and musical scores of tangos for voice and piano.
  - Cage, John Perpetual Tango, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Score and parts for violin, trumpet, alto saxophone, bass clarinet, percussion, contrabass and a piano reduction. (Box 3, Folder 144)
  - Gade, Jacob, 1879-1963 Jalousie, Arranged by Mikhashoff Publisher: Gade & Warny, 1925 (Publisher no.: G. & W. 2) Parts only for clarinet in A, trumpet in A, alto saxophone in E♭, percussion, violin, accordion, piano, contrabass. Additional parts for flute, trumpet II in A, trombone, violin II, violin obligato, viola, violoncello. (Box 3, Folder 145)
  - Krenek, Ernst, 1900- Reverie Tango from Act I of Jonny spielt auf, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Score and parts: Violin, clarinet, alto saxophone, accordion, percussion, piano, contrabass. (Box 3, Folder 146)
  - Lehrer, Tom, 1928- Masochism Tango, Publisher: Tom Lehre, 1968 Score for voice and piano. (Box 3, Folder 147)
  - Nancarrow, Conlon, 1912- Tango, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Parts for violin, B♭ and bass clarinets, trumpet, B♭ soprano and E♭ baritone saxophones, vibraphone/marimba, piano, contrabass. (Box 3, Folder 148)
  - Rudhyar, Dane, 1895- Tango d'Antan, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Score and parts for violin and piano. (Box 3, Folder 149)
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- Exiles Café Tango (1984), Score for clarinet, tenor saxophone, trumpet, percussion, violin, piano, contrabass. (Box 3, Folder 150)
  - Satie, Erik, 1866-1925 Tango Perpetuel, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Score and parts for violin, trumpet, alto saxophone, bass clarinet, bowed crotale, contrabass. (Box 3, Folder 151)
  - Thomson, Virgil, 1896- Tango lullaby: a portrait of Mlle. Alvarez de Toledo, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Score and parts for violin, clarinet, trumpet (missing part), alto saxophone, vibraphone/marimba, percussion, piano, contrabass. (Box 3, Folder 152)
  - Warwick, M.C. Come Home Tonight, Score for voice and piano. (Box 3, Folder 153)
  - Weill, Kurt, 1900-1950 Tango - Ballade, Arranged by Mikhashoff in 1987. Score (only one page is available) for clarinet, alto saxophone, trumpet, soprano, accordion, violin, piano, contrabass and parts for voice and piano. (Box 3, Folder 154)
- Correspondence, 1983-1991, III.; Box 4, Folder 155-229
  Letters and agreements from composers invited to submit a tango to Mikhashoff and/or Ed Snider, arranged in alphabetical order. In addition, there is a seperate sequence of correspondence from a handful of composers to the Music Library, also arranged in alphabetical order.
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Ashley, Robert, 1930- (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Austin, Larry (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Babbitt, Milton, 1916- (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Barce, Ramón (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Bell, Larry, 1952- (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Biscardi, Chester (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Bright, Colin (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Bruce, Neely (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Bryars, Gavin (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Burgess, Anthony, 1917- (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Busby, Gerald (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Chadabe, Joel (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Christoff, Dimiter, 1933- (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Clarkson, Austin, Regarding the tango by Stefan Wolpe (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Composers Forum Inc. and Dance Theater Workshop (Box 4, Folder 169)
  - Davies, Hugh, 1943- (Box 4, Folder 170)
  - Détlefsen, Hans Christian, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 171)
  - Diamond, David, 1915- (Box 4, Folder 172)
  - Diemente, Edward (Box 4, Folder 173)
  - Drake, Jeremy, Regarding the tango by Iannis Xenakis (Box 4, Folder 174)
  - Edlund, Mikael, 1950- (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Fennelly, Brian (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Finch, Douglas (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Fine, Vivian, 1913- (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Finnissy, Michael (Box 4, Folder 179)
  - García, Orlando Jacinto (Box 4, Folder 180)
  - Genge, Anthony, 1952- (Box 4, Folder 181)
  - Gideon, Miriam, 1906- (Box 4, Folder 182)
  - Goeyvaerts, Karel (Box 4, Folder 183)
  - Goldstein, Malcolm, 1936- (Box 4, Folder 184)
  - Harris, Donald (Box 4, Folder 185)
  - Hill, Jackson, 1941- (Box 4, Folder 186)
  - Hodkinson, Sydney (Box 4, Folder 187)
  - Howard, Brian (Box 4, Folder 188)
  - Hunt, Jerry, 1943- (Box 4, Folder 189)
  - Jack, Adrian (Box 4, Folder 190)
  - Jeney, Zoltán, 1943- (Box 4, Folder 191)
  - Johnson, Tom, 1939- (Box 4, Folder 192)
  - Kotík, Petr (Box 4, Folder 193)
  - Krauze, Zygmunt (Box 4, Folder 194)
  - Kurtz, Eugene, 1923- (Box 4, Folder 195)
  - Lee, Noël, 1924- (Box 4, Folder 196)
  - Leeuw, Ton de, 1926- (Box 4, Folder 197)
  - Loudova, Ivana (Box 4, Folder 198)
  - Mellnäs, Arne (Box 4, Folder 199)
  - Melnyk, Lubomyr (Box 4, Folder 200)
  - Mencherini, Fernando, 1949- (Box 4, Folder 201)
  - Monk, Meredith (Box 4, Folder 202)
  - Mumford, Jeffrey, 1955- (Box 4, Folder 203)
  - Newlin, Dika, 1923- (Box 4, Folder 204)
  - Nichifor, Serbin (Box 4, Folder 205)
  - Nobre, Marlos, 1939- (Box 4, Folder 206)
  - Noon, David, 1946- (Box 4, Folder 207)
  - Nørgård, Per, 1932- (Box 4, Folder 208)
  - Ortiz, William (Box 4, Folder 209)
  - Palmer, Robert, 1915- (Box 4, Folder 210)
  - Rautavaara, Einojuhani, 1928- (Box 4, Folder 211)
  - Rosenhaus, Steve (Box 4, Folder 212)
  - Ross, Valerie (Box 4, Folder 213)
  - Ruders, Poul, 1949- (Box 4, Folder 214)
  - Rzewski, Frederic (Box 4, Folder 215)
  - Sahl, Michael, 1934- (Box 4, Folder 216)
  - Sauguet, Henri, 1901- (Box 4, Folder 217)
  - Schwartz, Elliott, 1936- (Box 4, Folder 218)
  - Sepos, Charles, 1950- (Box 4, Folder 219)
  - Silsbee, Ann (Box 4, Folder 220)
  - Sullivan, Ken (Box 4, Folder 221)
  - Tcherepnin, Ivan (Box 4, Folder 222)
  - Thorkell, Sigurbjörnsson, 1938- (Box 4, Folder 223)
  - Thorne, Francis (Box 4, Folder 224)
  - Tiensuu, Jukka (Box 4, Folder 225)
  - Tisné, Antoine (Box 4, Folder 226)
  - Vigeland, Nils (Box 4, Folder 227)
  - Wielecki, Tadeusz (Box 4, Folder 228)
  - Zimmermann, Walter, 1949- (Box 4, Folder 229)
- Research materials, 1 983-1991, IV.; Box 5, Folder 230-232
  Sources used as research, including magazine articles, newspaper clippings, journal articles, sources of the images used as slides during performances, and music scores of 10 tangos not performed as a part of this collection.
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Magazine articles, journal articles, newspaper clippings, and playbill for the broadway show, Tango Argentina (Box 5, Folder 230)
  - Images from print sources (Box 5, Folder 231)
  - Photograph of unknown bandoneon player by photographer Camilla van Zuylen, Buenos Aires, March 1985 (Box 5, Folder 232)
- Study scores, 1983-1991, V.; Box 5, Folder 233-242
  Arranged alphabetically by composer name.
  - Atkinson, Condit R It Still Takes Two to do the Hustle, Rhumba, Cha Cha, Tango: Piano Duets G. Schirmer, 1978. Publisher no.: 19089 (Box 5, Folder 233)
  - Barber, Samuel, 1910- Hesitation Tango G. Schirmer, 1978. Publisher no.: 19089 (Box 5, Folder 234)
  - Gade, Jacob, 1879-1963. Tango charmeuse Gade & Warny, 1925. Publisher no.: G. & W. 9 (Box 5, Folder 235)
  - Jouannest, Gérard. Funeral Tango (Le Tango Funebre) Hill and Range Songs, Inc., 1968. Publisher no.: 130-19318 (Box 5, Folder 236)
  - Logatti, Lorenzo. El Irresistible (Box 5, Folder 237)
  - Moore, Edward C. Pavlowana, in The Journal (Box 5, Folder 238)
  - Nazareth, Ernesto. Dengozo: Maxixe Tango (Box 5, Folder 239)
  - Stertin, E. L'Exhilaration (Box 5, Folder 240)